THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
Did you hear about the fire the other day?
前天失火的事你听说了吗？
Quite an accomplishment for Lihaku, I'd say.
李白那家伙 表现得真出色啊
I never thought he'd solve it.
真没想到竟然是他解决的
Seems like, according to rumors,
谣传这件事得以顺利解决
a maidservant played a big part in solving it.
似乎是有个婢女扮演了关键角色
A maidservant?
婢女？
Apparently it's Sir Jinshi's assigned servant.
据说是壬氏大人的贴身侍女
Is that so?
是哦 真的吗？
Speaking of Sir Jinshi, he bought out a courtesan from the Verdigris House.
说到壬氏大人 他之前替绿青馆的娼妓赎了身
I heard she's an intellectual beauty with a cold look!
听说是个冷若冰霜的知性美女
That's what the guys who saw her said!
看到的人都在热议呢
-Oh… -Sir Lakan?
-哦… -罗汉大人？
Could you tell me a little more?
那个传闻 能跟我说详细点吗？
Xiaomao, can I talk to you for a bit?
小猫 能借一步说话吗？
What is it, Sir Gaoshun?
高顺大人 怎么了吗？
I want you to take a look at this.
我想请你替我看看这个
Documents on an old case?
是过去案件的资料啊
A merchant family ten years ago
十年前 有个商家
got food poisoning from a dish of puffer fish and vegetables.
因为吃了河豚鱼脍 发生了食物中毒事件
Poison from puffer fish…
吃了河豚而中毒啊…
That tingly poison feels so good!
那种麻麻的中毒感最棒了
I want some right now…
啊…好想吃哦
I'll take you to a restaurant that serves a similar dish.
下次再带你去吃这类饭馆就是了
So, what's happening?
这起案件怎么了吗？
I was involved with this case for work
以前这个案子发生的时候
back when it happened.
我因为工作的关系而参与其中
A very similar case to this happened recently,
最近又发生了非常类似的案件
and a former coworker asked for my help.
我以前的同僚便来找我商量
A similar case?
类似的案件？
A government official ate a dish of puffer fish and vegetables,
一位官员吃了河豚鱼脍
and is in a comatose state now.
现在陷入了昏迷状态
A comatose state…?
昏迷状态…
Excuse me, but…
非常抱歉 高顺大人
Is it okay that I'm hearing about this?
我知道这件事不会不妥吗？
It's not a problem.
这不成问题
You're someone who knows your position.
因为小猫是个明白自己立场的人
So it's confidential, huh?
也就是不许说出去
And you've already heard this much.
而且话都说到这儿了
Do you really want to cut off a story about poison right here?
既然事关毒物 就此打住的话 你忍得住吗？
Please. Go right ahead.
请继续说吧
This time, the dish contained
这次的鱼脍
parboiled puffer fish skin and flesh.
用的是川烫过的河豚皮与肉
He ate that, and then went into a coma.
说是官员吃了之后 便陷入昏迷状态
He ate puffer fish flesh?
他吃的是河豚肉？
Most of the poison is in its organs, like the liver.
毒素较多的部分 应该是肝脏之类的内脏
Yes. It was the skin and flesh.
没错 是鱼皮和鱼肉
The flesh shouldn't contain that much poison…
鱼肉含有的毒素应该比较少
There might be poison in the flesh
不过依照种类和生长环境不同
depending on the type of fish and its environment…
鱼肉确实也可能会含有毒素
This case doesn't seem strange.
这件案子看来没有疑点
The thing is… In both this case and the one ten years ago,
问题是…这次和上次的案件
the chef insists he didn't use any puffer fish in the food.
厨子都坚称都没有用到河豚入菜
Oh? That's interesting.
这样就有意思了
There are more similarities.
共通点还不只如此
Both victims…
两位受害者
The government official and the merchant
这次的官员和上次的商人
both loved fine dining and delicacies.
都是偏爱珍馐的饕客
They ate raw fish often,
他们平时就经常享用生鲜鱼肉
and loved puffer fish.
也相当喜爱河豚
After they collapsed, they found all the fish organs and skin
案件发生后 有人在厨房的垃圾桶里
in the kitchen trash,
找到了鱼皮和内脏
so it was proven they didn't eat the liver.
所以证明了他们没有吃到肝脏
Both the chefs from the two cases claim that
这两起案件的厨子都声称
the puffer fish was used for dinner the previous night
河豚是前一天晚餐使用的食材
and that they used different fish for the fish and vegetables dish,
鱼脍使用的是另一种鱼
to assert their innocence.
并藉此主张自己的清白
But there were no witnesses to their claims.
但没有任何可以作证的证人
30 minutes after the government official finished his meal,
官员在吃完料理的两刻钟后
he developed symptoms of poisoning, collapsed,
出现了中毒症状而倒下
and was found going into convulsions.
被发现的时候已全身痉挛
I didn't expect them to investigate this thoroughly…
意外地调查的很仔细呢
There are many good-for-nothing bureaucrats
明明有不少官员只会随便调查
who investigate carelessly and make up a culprit…
找个替罪羔羊交差了事
What do you think?
你有何看法？
The symptoms align with puffer fish poison.
症状虽然跟河豚的毒很像
But I don't have enough details…
但只凭这些也实在…
Sir Gaoshun, could you collect more information?
高顺大人 能麻烦您再多搜集一些情报吗？
Of course. I'll investigate more.
我知道了 我会再继续调查
During this time of the year,
现在这个季节
it's not rare for cooks to leave out food waste for a few days.
将厨余摆个几天也并不奇怪
They claim to have used another fish.
他们说是用另一种鱼
They found some fish scraps, so it makes sense…
并且也发现了这些鱼的残渣 姑且也合乎道理
What were you talking about?
你们在聊什么？
That face is pretty hurtful, even for me.
这种表情 就算是我也会受伤的
You were listening to Gaoshun very intently.
你好像听高顺说话听得津津有味啊
Most people listen intently when it's an interesting conversation.
内容有趣的话 总是会吸引听众的
Hey, wait a minute. You often cut me off…
等一下 你明明经常在我说话时…
All right, then. It's late.
那么 时间也不早了
I'll be going home.
请恕小的退下了
Hey, I'm not done talking to you…
喂 我话还没说完…
Hey, now. Don't move.
哎呀 别乱动哦
Stay still, all right?
请您坐好
Xiaomao. About that case…
小猫 关于昨天的事…
Here is the recipe.
这是食谱
The servants say that
佣人作证说
most recipes served to their patron are recorded here.
会端给主人的菜肴食谱 大多都写在这里面了
Thank you.
谢谢您
"Add shredded vegetables to parboiled fish and mix with vinegar."
“鱼肉川烫后 加入切丝蔬菜 再用醋拌匀”
There's nothing strange about this recipe.
鱼脍的做法没有可疑之处
There are several types of vinegar mixture combinations,
虽然写了好几种醋的配方
but the ingredient list is not specific.
但没有列出详细的材料
Probably because the fish and vegetables
可能是因为随着季节不同
they can obtain depends on the season.
能用的鱼肉和蔬菜 也会有所不同的关系
But with this recipe,
这样一来 最重要的部分
we don't know what they used in the dish.
用了什么食材也不得而知呢
You don't know?
不得而知吗？
Looks like he wants to join.
他好像也想加入呢
What is it that you don't know?
所以 是什么不得而知？
You haven't eaten your meal yet.
您还没用正餐呢
I know.
我知道
He's being very childish.
真是有够孩子气
-When did this occur? -About a week ago.
-案件发生的时间是？ -大约一周前
So did they use winter vegetables in the dish,
若是冬天的蔬菜 鱼脍的食材
like radishes and carrots?
应该是白萝卜或红萝卜之类的？
They say they used seaweed.
他们说用的是海藻
Seaweed?
海藻？
Yes, seaweed.
对 海藻
If they like delicacies,
如果他们喜欢珍馐
they might have used some rare seaweed.
就很可能会选用一些特殊的海藻
Is it possible to take a look inside that home's kitchen?
可以的话 能否到那户人家的厨房看看？
Sir Gaoshun told me to come here…
高顺大人要我来此处
So I've heard. I'm Basen.
我是马闪 事情我听说了
I'm Maomao.
我是猫猫
We're going to the mansion now,
接下来就前往官员宅邸
but starting here, you're my "servant."
但从现在开始 你就是我的“婢女”
-Okay? Don't try anything silly. -Yes, sir.
-明白吗？不要擅自行动 -我知道了
Once we arrive, the mansion's servant will show you around the kitchen.
我们抵达之后 宅邸的佣人会带你去厨房
Yes, sir.
是
As expected of Sir Gaoshun. He works fast.
真不愧是高顺大人 做事真是明快
Speaking of…
但是
I haven't seen this soldier before.
是没见过面的武官啊
He reminds me of someone…
总觉得很像谁…
Looks like he doesn't like me very much.
他好像对我心怀疑虑呢
Whatever.
算了 无妨
Here is the kitchen.
这儿就是厨房
We haven't used it since the poisoning.
发生中毒事件后 就再也没有用过了
Hey!
喂
Don't come in here! Get out!
不准随便进来 出去！
What are you doing? Did you bring them here?
你在做什么？ 是你带这些家伙过来的吗？
We got permission from the lady.
我们已获得了夫人的许可
This is our job.
再说我们是奉命行事
Is that true?
真的吗？
Can we enter?
我们可以进去了吗？
Or would that cause an inconvenience?
还是说有何不便之处？
Do as you like.
随便你吧
Who is that?
那个人是谁？
He is our patron's younger brother.
他是主人的弟弟
After Patron went into a coma,
主人昏迷之后
the lady has been bedridden from exhaustion,
夫人也因为劳累过度而卧病在床
and his brother has been managing this mansion.
因此现在由弟弟代为管事
I see.
原来如此
-Sir Basen? -Yeah.
-马闪大人 -嗯
Seems like the chef already cleaned the cooking supplies.
看来厨子已经将厨具都清理过了
Other than that…
除此之外…
What is this?
这是什么？
Oh, that's what Patron likes.
那是主人爱吃的食物
It was his favorite. He ate it often.
他非常喜爱 也很常吃
So I don't think it's poisonous…
所以我不认为那会有毒…
Doesn't look like he's lying.
看起来不像是说谎
You got that?
听见没？
Are you done? Leave already.
没事的话 就快请回吧
Yes, we're done.
说得对
Sorry for the trouble.
抱歉打扰了
Why did you back down so easily?
你怎么这么轻易就作罢了？
Oh, I don't think I backed down.
我可没有作罢呢
You brought that here?
你把那东西带出来了？
This is really strange.
这个有些问题
It's too early in the season to get this seaweed.
要采收这种海藻 时节还太早
But it's not something that'll last this long
但即使用盐腌渍
even after it's been soaked in salt.
也不可能保存到现在这个季节
I see.
原来如此
I don't think it was caught around here.
我想 这应该不是在本地采到的
Maybe it was imported from the south through trade, or….
例如说 也许是通过交易从南方进货的
It would be nice if we can find out where it was imported from.
若是能知道从哪儿进货就好了
Looks like he got it.
看来他知道该做什么了
So now, it's time for me to do my job.
那么 我也该做我该做的事了
What is this?
这是什么？
I brought this seaweed from the mansion.
是从官员宅邸带回的海藻
I divided them into two and soaked them in water.
我事先分为两份后 并泡在水里
Why is Sir Jinshi here?
为什么壬氏大人也在？
I looked into it.
经过调查后
The seaweed was imported from the south.
海藻果然是从南方带来的
According to servants,
根据佣人的证言
their patron didn't usually eat this seaweed in the winter.
他们的主人在冬天时 不曾吃过这种海藻
The cooks also said
厨子也宣称
it's the same type of seaweed they use all the time,
这和他们平常使用的海藻种类相同
and it's not poisonous.
不可能会有毒
Just because it's the same seaweed doesn't mean it's not poisonous.
即使是同样的海藻 也不代表没有毒
Perhaps it's not customary
也许在南方
to eat this seaweed in the south.
并没有吃这种海藻的习惯
What if a merchant learned this is a foodie bureaucrat's favorite,
如果某个商人知道了 这种海藻是某个饕客官员的最爱
and had the locals make a salted seaweed in order to make money?
为了赚钱 而特地要当地人制作盐渍海藻呢？
Why would that be a problem?
那会有什么问题？
In this world, there are ways
在这世上
to make poisonous things not poisonous.
有办法可让毒物变成无毒
For example, eels are poisonous in their natural state.
例如 鳗鱼本来是有毒的
But you can draw their blood or cook them to make them edible.
但只要放血或加热便能食用
As for this seaweed,
而这种海藻
it needs to be soaked in limewater.
得浸泡在石灰水中才行
What we have here is seaweed soaked in limewater,
这儿所准备的 分别是浸泡过石灰水
and seaweed not soaked in limewater.
与没有浸泡的海藻
What are you doing!
你在做什么？
I should be fine… I think.
不要紧的 应该吧
What do you mean, you think?
“应该”是什么意思？
Don't worry. I have an emetic right here.
放心吧 我有准备催吐剂
That's not something to be proud of!
别自信满满地说这种话啊！
-Gaoshun! -Hey!
-高顺！ -在
Wait…
等一下…
Throw up!
吐出来！
I was going to test whether a one-night soak
明明只要吃了 就能确认
would get rid of the poison…
泡了一晚是否足以去掉毒素的说…
All right, let's reconvene.
好的 我们重新再来吧
Here's a question.
这儿有个问题
Who was the person who asked the trader to bring
向贸易商提议带来盐渍海藻的人
the salted seaweed?
是谁呢？
If it was the Patron himself who ordered it, then it's his own fault.
如果是官员本人要求的 那就是他自作自受
But if it wasn't…
但如果不是的话…
Importing ingredients from an area where they don't eat it
从没有食用习惯的地方订制
is always risky, isn't it?
危险性一定相当高吧
I understand.
我明白了
Everyone here is quick-witted.
在场的所有人都很聪明
I don't need to say more.
无需再多说了
Looks like this case is closed…
总之 这样案子就告一段落了
The culprit was the official's younger brother.
结果 犯人是昏迷官员的弟弟
Once we found who the seller was,
我们找到贸易商后
he confessed and said he bought it.
他就招认是自己买的
He said he did it because he felt overlooked as the younger brother,
动机是因为他身为次子 而经常遭到漠视
and wanted to get rid of the older brother.
所以认为长子非常碍眼
Tale as old as time.
这是常有的事
But how did a man who attempted murder for such a shallow reason
但为了这么肤浅的原因 而企图杀人的人
find out about the poison in the seaweed?
是如何发现海藻含毒的呢？
Apparently he learned it by chance from someone next to him at a pub.
听说是在酒家喝酒时 邻座的客人无意间告诉他的
"By chance," huh…?
“无意间”是吗？
In the end, I didn't get to eat the poisonous seaweed…
到头来 还是没机会 尝到有毒的海藻
But what should I make with that?
话说回来 要用来做什么呢？
That brown mushroom growing out of the dried insect…
那个从虫干长出来的枯叶色菇类…
Medicinal alcohol?
要拿来做药酒吗？
Or pills?
还是药丸好呢？
Welcome home, sir!
欢迎回来
Welcome home… home… home…
欢迎回来…
Huh?
咦？
What's going on?
发生什么事了？
This isn't my fault.
不是我害的哦
You look tired, Young Master.
您看起来很累呢
I have a lot of work left…
公务累积了不少
But there's someone I can't get along with.
但有个人 该说是个性不合吗？
We disagree on everything.
总是和我意见相左
So there are people even you can't get along with, Sir Jinshi?
壬氏大人也有应付不来的人吗？
He's a very intelligent high military official.
对方是个绝顶聪明的军府高官
He's from a good family,
家世显赫
but won't marry even though he's over 40.
但年过四十仍不娶妻
He adopted his nephew and has him managing the household.
收了个侄子做为养子 将家中事务交由养子管理
He's a famous eccentric.
是个出了名的怪人
Over 40…
年过四十…
A high military official… An eccentric?
军府高官…怪人？
His only interests are
若要说他的兴趣
Go, chess, and gossip.
就是下围棋、将棋和聊八卦
He nitpicks and barges in
很爱挑人毛病 或擅闯对方居所
so that he can extend the deadline to sign off on cases.
拖延时间 不让议案盖印
Looks like I'm his next target.
最近他似乎是盯上我了
He sits in my office every day…
每天都来我的书房待着…
Okay. I'm going to forget about this.
好 忘了吧
Remembering won't do me any good.
即使回想起来 也没什么好处
But even if I try to forget,
但就算我忘掉
my bad feelings usually come true…
常有的不祥预感总是会成真
We already signed off on the case.
议案应该已经通过了才是
It's hard to see flowers in the winter.
冬天要赏花实在困难
That's why I'm here. For the flowers.
因此我想不如改访此处
This man's name is Lakan.
此人名叫罗汉
He's a general.
是一名军师
Looks like he's pestering me
而他缠上我的原因
because I hired Maomao, who has connections to The Verdigris House.
似乎是因为我雇了 与绿青馆有关系的猫猫作为婢女
Speaking of,
说到这个…
I have an old friend from The Verdigris House.
我以前在绿青馆有个老相好
That's unexpected.
这倒是令人意外
I assumed he wasn't interested in this sort of thing.
我以为他对这类事情不感兴趣
Who was this courtesan?
是什么样的娼妓？
I didn't mean to ask.
不小心问出口了
She was a good courtesan.
她是个很好的娼妓
She was good at Go and chess.
擅长围棋和将棋
I could beat her at chess, but I always lost at Go.
将棋我能赢过她 但围棋却总是输给她
To beat you, Sir General, she must've been good.
能赢过军师大人 想必非常厉害
I didn't think I could meet
我想我再也遇不到
a more interesting woman than her, so I considered buying her out.
那么有意思的女人了 所以考虑过要替她赎身
But the world isn't that easy.
但天不从人愿
Two rich men with unique preferences
有两个好事的有钱人
kept raising her price, like it was a bidding war.
在争相出价 让赎金水涨船高
How unfortunate.
那可真是…
Buying out a courtesan could cost
娼妓的赎金
as much as building a whole villa.
有时高到足以建造一座离宫
She was a really strange courtesan…
她是位奇特的娼妓
What is he trying to get at, talking about this?
但他说这些事 究竟是想要说什么？
She was skilled, but didn't sell her body.
她只卖艺不卖身
She doesn't even think of customers as customers.
不只如此 她甚至不把客人当客人看
Even when pouring tea to customers, she had an arrogant look,
即使给客人倒茶 也是用着一副高傲的神情看人
as if she was giving alms to a lowly peasant.
像是在施舍贱民一样
But there are men that get infatuated by that sort of thing.
但不少人却因此被迷得神魂颠倒
I was one of those men.
说起来 我也是其中一人哪
It sent shivers down my spine. So divine!
那种背脊一阵阵酥麻的感觉 真是欲罢不能啊
I wanted to have her one day.
那时我想 我总有一天要得到她
I couldn't give up on her.
结果我无法对她死心
So I used a bit of a dirty trick.
不得已而用了一点肮脏手段
-A dirty trick? -I couldn't afford her.
-什么意思？ -贵到付不起的话
So I just needed to lower her price.
只要降低她的身价就行了
I decreased her scarcity value.
我降低了她的稀有价值
Want to know how?
想知道我用了何种方法吗？
You said this much, and you won't tell me?
都说到这个地步了 还要卖关子吗？
Before that, I have a favor to ask.
在继续之前 我有一事相求
What is it?
什么事？
I heard you recently hired a very interesting maid.
听说你最近雇用了一位 非常有意思的婢女
I hear she's good at solving mysteries.
好像是莫名地擅长解谜吧？
I had a friend who was the court purveyor goldsmith.
我认识一位宫廷御用的雕金师
He passed away the other day,
他日前过世了
without assigning a successor.
此人没有指定确切的继承人
He had three children that were his apprentices,
他有三个孩子 都是他的徒弟
but he died without telling them his secret technique, those poor things.
但他在死前未能把堪称秘技的技术 传授下去 令我于心不忍
It seems like his mysterious will
他那意味深长的遗言
is some kind of clue.
我想一定是某种线索
This has been bothering me for a bit.
这事让我十分困扰
What are you trying to say?
你到底想说什么？
It's nothing, really.
没什么 不是什么大事
I'm just wondering if it's possible to know what this secret technique is.
我只是在想 是否有办法 找出那秘传技术究竟是什么
For example,
例如
perhaps your clever maid could take a look.
请某位头脑灵光的婢女帮忙调查一下
Before I say anything,
总之
please tell me the details.
能否先将整件事详细告诉我？
It's pouring.
雨好大啊
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "Lead."
下一集 《铅》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：欧德慧